meet
on the meeting minutes for May 12th.
Okay. If none, all in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Okay. Are there any disclosures,
conflicts of interest that anyone would
like to make? Nope. Let's move on to
audience business.
Is there
anyone in the audience that would like
to address the board?
Um, my name is Don Morris. I've been a
Cheyenne resident since 1972
and I live 717 Frontier Park Avenue
which is right behind the Deming
Elementary School which is up for sale.
So the reason I came was to see what had
to be done and if someone wanted to
purchase the building and modify it or
if also if someone wanted to purchase
the building and um demolish it and then
build what they needed to do. And Aaron
has pretty much answered my questions
very succinctly. So, I don't have too
much to do except as I understand it,
the time that the Historic Preservation
Board would possibly get involved would
be if someone went through the
procedures and needed to demolish the
building.
>> Yeah, that's correct.
>> Okay, I think I've got everything down,
so I don't want to take your time, but I
really appreciate coming in and speaking
to you, and I'll try to keep track of
what's going on. Thank you very much.
>> Thank you. Thanks for coming.
>> You and Chair, I just wanted to add one
more thing. When they do do a zone
change, they are required to notify
surrounding properties with owners
within 300 ft. So, you should get a
notification for that.
Do we have a city council representative
tonight or
Charles? You are now city rep city
council representative. Okay.
>> Apologies for being a little bit late.
Um
yes, council member Esco had mentioned
that he has some conflicts uh right now.
So I was going to give some updates. Um,
for those of you who have been following
the council meetings, they've been long
recently. We have a lot of public input
that is coming into place regarding
different annexations and resonings and
um other developments, actions that
could be or are for data center related
development. So their focus is on trying
to uh hear the public and also provide
additional information on what's going
on. So that's been occupying a lot of
time. Uh two other items have been
considered that are development related
and this is partly overlapping with with
my item as well. One of those was an
ordinance to allow carports to be
constructed in front yards. Essentially
they had very minimum design standards.
So they essentially resembled what you
could purchase at Menards and what
Menards would have on display for a cart
rack, but up to 300 ft in size. That
failed yesterday, so that did not move
forward. Um the ones you presently see
in front yards right now, even in
historic districts, even just blocks
away from here, none of those have been
permitted or have proper approvals.
We're not planning on jumping up and
enforcing any of those right now. Our
enforcement process on those is more
complaint driven. We have another
amendment that's moving forward on it's
been approved by second reading and
that's on historic horse racing
which continues to move forward and this
will essentially establish a priority
zone or a receiving zone for historic
horse racing facilities where they're
trying to locate them in major corridors
that have easy access to uh other areas
in the region to bring in people from
out of state or out of town and also
areas where they're trying to redevelop
like the Reed Route Corridor and the
15th Street Experience Area. The
existing ones that are in place right
now, all of those will be grandfathered.
Um well, for the time being, they'll be
allowed to continue. Uh they will follow
a process as uh which is parallel to
state statute, which will require them
to go back for approval in front of the
governing body by December 31st of 2027.
uh the way the uh proposed ordinance is
drafted, it has a couple of flaws right
now, but those will be corrected uh at
the meeting on Monday of the public
services committee and none of the
existing or the proposed facilities that
we have right now would be negatively
affected by those design uh standards.
Some other items that the council has
been considering is there is the budget
which was approved last night.
So I believe I'm still in the budget. So
is Miss Fagan here.
>> We are all in the the department's still
in the budget. Um nothing sign
significant has changed. Uh so we're
continuing to move forward with um our
budget as it has been the last couple of
years. Uh there um is some investment in
staff that is occurring. There is a cost
of living. Well, not a cost of living.
There is a merit increase that has been
approved citywide as part of retention
program trying to make sure that we keep
our associates so we're not having to
retrain everybody every year or every
two years because training new people in
organizations is very expensive and
timeconuming for everybody.
Um, also last night there's a pretty
hefty discussion on um our Belvoir
Ranch. Uh, Councilman Tom Crave has
wanted to open up a portion of that for
development, primarily economic
development. And the mayor was
authorized the ability to um,
essentially
uh, give people access to the Belvore
for exploratory purposes relating to
development. That means they could do uh
engineering study to look at the soils.
They could do geotechnical stuff to look
at the soils. They could also do
cultural surveys to identify if there's
anything um on site on a development
area where it could have cultural
significance like Indian rings,
arrowheads, other different things that
you will you can find on the Belvore.
So, those are some items that we're
we're moving forward with on that. Um
there has been a lot of other stuff that
has been going on but it's primarily
been overshadowed by the the data center
uh stuff. Um a moratorum was attempted
since last time that we all met and that
failed on second reading. Um so continue
to move forward with with educational
campaigns.
>> Does anyone have any questions for
Charles?
I have just one one question about the
the Belvore Ranch. Um the the hiking
trails that are they still opening this
summer? Do you know anything about that?
>> Yes. Uh board member Chrysler, that is
that is great question. Yes, they are on
target for opening this summer. I do not
know the exact timeline, but they will
be open this summer. I know we said that
last spring that it will be open this
summer. I remind you all that's still
spring right now for about 13 or 12 more
days. So note will be um moving forward.
Also the uh governing body or actually
it's the council the council is the nine
the governing bodies when the mayor is
included but the city council is looking
at a memorial for uh council member Roy
Ball who had passed away last year. One
of his uh pride and joy projects was the
Belvore Ranch. uh he had a special
allocation of funds that we utilized to
do a lot of um early um projects with
the ranch. So there will be a memorial
that is looked at to be placed out there
at the trail head. So that's something
that we will I know the council is
working on right now. I don't know if
it'll be in conjunction with a grand
opening or if it will be uh separate and
independent.
>> And then just sorry um a follow up on
that. Um, I think at least I and I think
probably the rest of the board would be
interested in if there's any like
historic or cultural interpretation that
is maybe going to go out there or if
that hasn't been planned like getting
involved in like, you know, like an
interpretive sign about the history of
the area, history of the ranch, um,
something like that. I think I I would
just be curious to hear what the plans
are for something along those lines and
if that's if there are no plans for that
if there's that's something that we as a
board could um get involved in
chair uh board member Chrysler I can
comfortably say that there is nothing
out there right now that celebrates the
culture. I I know that there's nothing
out there and there has been a lot of
discussion that we have had internally
as staff as to if we point out some
areas of cultural significance like a
teepee ring which are the rock rings
that surrounded some of the largest
teepeees back in the day there's still
areas out there but we started to point
those out could they be defaced or could
do we draw attention to them so there's
been a little bit of discussion on how
that looks I do know there were areas
when we were looking at placing an
emergency response tower out there where
we did find uh remnants of partial arrow
heads where they had started and then
they had broken or they had not been
done where you can see that they're
doing work. But there definitely is the
ability to um provide um some
interpretive stuff. Um I think it would
be great to have the historic
preservation board
uh as part of that process. And as we
get this um moving forward, I think we
could um work with the I wonder who the
project manager is right now. I think
Who is the project manager? It's Dustin.
It's uh Dustin Humphre. He's our
department. He's been managing the
project. We can talk to him on next
steps because right now the first steps
was getting the trail head complete,
getting the trails in place and getting
signage put together. And that was
sitting about 90% last fall. So it
should be at 100% and we can look at how
to elevate it to Belvwar 2.0.
>> Gary,
>> is the missile base part of that
property?
chair um boards or chair through you to
board member Sims.
The property surrounds the missile
silos. There are two silo buildings out
there in an old power plant. Um about
eight years ago, the assessor had done
no actually about six five or six years
ago, the assessor had done some research
and they changed the land ownership back
to the federal government because of
some deed restrictions. So, they're
technically under the federal
government's um ownership right now, but
we still have access to them. Like, we
have our own lock and key on the
buildings uh to keep people out. Um but
there have been discussions about
looking at how we could make that some
type of interpretive site um out there.
Uh if anyone has connections with state
parks,
uh we have wanted to lean on them and
say, "Hey, you have one missile silo.
How about this one? Um, [snorts] but it
could be challenging to do that
restoration.
>> They aren't exactly silos. They are
buildings laid down like that. And
actually, there's three of them out
there. And there was a contamination
problem at one time because they used to
just
>> blow the fuel out of it when they
changed them and run it into a ditch.
And so there's that problem, but that's
a real historic site. It's one of the
original Atlas sites. And um and it's
very dangerous in this respect that
people have been stripping it for 50
years now. So
>> yes, that's that's accurate. With the
old at the Atlas facility, it is the
older above ground buildings, they have
the roof that would essentially open up
and then the the missile would elevate.
I like to compare it to that old movie
Spies Like Us sort of, but this was the
American side of it where you had that
missile that would or that would be um
up there and what would happen is they
would bring them to alert, they would
test them, they do a burn and then they
would essentially clean the engines and
that would go into a discharge pit and
then that had TCE which is a
environmental contaminant and that TCE
is in the ground and it's actually um
moved and migrated across a good portion
of that north um western portion of
Bellevor Ranch. Uh the federal
government is actively monitoring that
TCE plume and tri no terracon I believe
is the consultant that goes out there
and is doing uh tests. But in order to
mitigate uh tce which is what the
contaminant is um it's actually
relatively easy. It's just uh costly and
timeconuming. Essentially is bringing
ground water to the surface essentially
bubbling it and oxygen oxygenating it
and then it releases the tce and it can
go in the it's goes in the atmosphere
and it's not harmful to deal with that
direction. Um, but there have been
discussions about how to
>> and just
>> pressure them to go quicker.
>> And just for some historical
significance, if you go to the Atlas or
no, the Eagle Bar down by the pump
house, if you see that big tower,
they've got their sign on. That's one of
the original missile
>> cradles.
>> Cradles that was inside those buildings.
>> Very cool.
>> Yeah. Next time you do drive by or walk
by, look up and you'll totally see it.
You can't miss it. I believe the city of
Gley
may maintain an atlas facility off of US
34.
I've wanted to go visited a couple
times, but their hours continue to be
reduced and
it's challenging to get out that where
where it's located, but I think they
have one. We can see about getting some
more information on that.
>> I I just have one more question on that.
it if the area is open for development.
Um, are the new trails going to be
protected and anything that they
potentially develop?
>> Chair, members of the board, I would
hope so. And I'm just laughing at some
of the things I've seen in the past. No,
I fully anticipate them to be protected.
This the area that they're looking at
for development is specifically out
east. So, it is the eastern portion. the
trails are on the northwestern uh sorry
southwestern portion. Um so areas that
would be subject for development are out
east at this time. Um and there has been
some discussion off of Harman Road just
very very lightly but we have not
actively looked at any any development
out there because there's uh some more
problems with getting utilities out that
direction. There's not natural gas out
that direction. Uh, and there's some
energy um issues with energy providers
because it does a switch through the
middle of the Belvoir Ranch from Black
Hills Energy to
I think it's High West is out there, I
believe. So, there's some differences in
utility providers that make some things
challenging out that direction.
>> Does anyone else have any further
questions? Okay. Um, I know I I don't
know if we want to jump ahead here, but
is David Palasio online? Do we want to
address him or so he doesn't have to sit
around?
>> Sure. He's not online. I did speak to
him yesterday. He said he was going to
be here, but Okay. Well, we can continue
on in the agenda. I just figured if he
was online and we wanted to go through
that now, that way he doesn't have to
stick around for everything. Okay. Um
I'm assuming that that also covers the
report from planning and development as
well.
>> Board uh chair board I can add real
quick. We have another face in the
audience back here. Uh this is Henry
Kopalinski
Cobblenick. Sorry, I knew I was going to
butcher that. I don't read it first time
I tried to say it.
>> The first part sort of right.
>> He is our he's our intern here. Um, he
is I'll let him introduce himself really
quick, but he'll be joining us for the
summer. You want to introduce yourself
and let them know your interest? That'd
be great.
>> Yes. Hi. [clears throat] Hi, members of
the board. I'm Henry Cobbalniki. I'm the
planning and development intern with the
planning department for the summer. I'm
a student at Kansas State University and
I'm originally from Laram.
>> Oh, awesome. Well, thank you for coming.
Awesome.
So other um department updates that we
have right now um we we're just
extremely busy working on different
development applications. We're still
being chased by urban agriculture. So
that is something that's on our agenda
to get done. Um we have
uh a comprehensive plan kickoff which we
just um had a selection committee review
eight proposals and all the proposals
were were very detailed. they're all
they're all uh qualified to really
create a a good plan, but a couple a few
of them roast a little bit higher than
the others. So, our next step is to try
to arrange for interviews for this
comprehensive plan. Um again the comp
plan is going to revisit our 2014 plan
and it's going to look at everything
from uh the land use plan for the future
like where development's going to go
where residential should hold firm and
stay where largecale industrial
development should go. Um but it also
will look at other um aspirational
um um items such as historic
preservation. do we target preservation
versus um you know new things like that.
So it have a lot of uh different
elements related to historic
preservation. It's also um supposed to
build on a lot of our existing plans
that we've done in recent years
including the parks and recreation plan.
It should complement that directly that
was approved in 2025. It should
complement our 2025 transportation
master plan which also was 2025 and it
will complement our 2024
DDA plan of development which this board
had some participation in because
there's a pretty strong historic
preservation element there. Um, and it
will, one more plan it will incorporate
is our
2012 bicycle and trails master plan,
which needs to rise back to the top as
cycling alternative modes is getting
very popular in this community.
So, that's all the updates I have unless
Aaron has anything.
>> Does anyone have any further questions?
Yep. We'll move on to our strategic
goals reports. Uh, National Register of
Historic Places.
Elizabeth or
>> Elizabeth maybe uh has an update.
>> I have handouts
along.
>> So, the documents that um I'm passing
out, this is for the African-American
study. Um, this is an example. The first
is kind of my um overview template that
I'm using for each property that I've
been able to identify. Um so you can see
at the top here is kind of just quick
and dirty so we know what's happening
but obviously the address, the years
active. Um does it still stand? What
were the purposes of it? Um how you know
how was it used essentially? um the
people associated with it and if it is
eligible for the National Register. Um
I've also included a map there. Um the
next section is property information.
You know, kind of the basics there,
location, what I've been able to find in
the county records, sandborn map
information, architectural style, and
history of the building as well. And
then we're popping into the people
associated. So all of their kind of
information. Um, and then also adding
census and city directory and history
for that as well. Um, and then of course
a bibliography because I have a tendency
of not saving that information. So I'm
trying to be on top of it. Um, so that's
what each property will have that
document attached to it. Um, the intent
with that is that's going to help me
write the narrative for each property as
well. So, this is kind of my like
big thing. Um, so I included an example
of what I have for one property. This is
the um,
excuse me, Lola West's property at 901
West 18th Street that is still standing.
Yay. Because not many are. [laughter]
Um, so you can see there's still some
gaps that I have there, but I'm trying
to also include maps of where each one
is located. You can see there the
property information is also included.
Um the county um records are fantastic
because they also some of them include
these layouts for us which is really
great. Um and you can see there I've got
sandborn information. I still have a
couple of things but you know Lola
West's information is being filled out
now. Um,
yeah. So, that's where that is, which
is good. I [laughter] hope.
>> No, that's awesome.
>> Um, so yeah, so um I probably won't
update on every single property as we go
on, but just so you guys can see what
each one um the documentation that will
be included. Now, while all this
information will go into the study, I'm
not sure at this point, but at least
we'll have it regardless, which I think
will be really helpful moving forward.
So, any questions on that project?
>> Yeah. So you're you're sort of using
this as a way to like organize the
research as you're gathering it and then
you'll take and so you'll do one of
these for each property that you're
looking at and then turn it into like a
written narrative that will go into the
overall
>> study. Exactly. So you can think of this
as kind of like a very intense outline
if you will for each property. So this
is what I'm using. Yes. To become the
narrative for each one. And are you
still is is everything still sort of
like going
>> oh yeah
>> going well? And I I know before we had
talked about like I would be willing to
help you if you need any help on stuff
and so it just that offer still stands
but um otherwise yeah thanks for uh
sharing what you've been working on.
>> Yeah. Um I think one thing and we can
talk you know outside of the meeting too
is going through all the census records
and gathering address for people
identified within the community. Um
that's going to be a big lift. So
really, it's just highlighting things
for me would be really helpful, too. And
so I've um been downloading the census
records that we have um but we have to
go through every single one obviously
because people change and addresses
change. So,
>> to build off of what Josh offered, um,
if you need some assistance with
identifying like architectural style, I
could I could definitely help with that.
>> That would be great. Thank you,
>> chair.
>> Just a sideline, there's a wonderful
picture of that property being moved
down Snyder being pulled by mules and um
I don't think there's a date on that,
but it was premotorized
vehicles and I don't know where it was
moved in from. There was some talk. It
came from right over here. Great
picture.
>> Great.
>> Yeah, that picture's in the the
archives. Um, also, I don't know if you
probably noticed that Rick Ewig just
published a book this week about Lola
West um and about this this building in
particular. So, there's a bunch of new
research that he did that is just coming
out right now.
>> That's fantastic. Yeah, if you could
send that to me, that would be great.
>> Sure. Yeah.
Um, so I suppose if it is helpful, I can
share these. If people know of other
things that I might have missed, um,
that would be really fantastic.
Any other questions for Elizabeth on
this portion?
Is there any update for airport
terminal? Is that just kind of ongoing?
Nothing new and exciting to report?
>> There's lots of exciting things.
>> Um, not really. Um, so I did create
started a document um, essentially like
an easier form to fill out than the
National Register form because it's the
format doesn't matter. It's not easily
done. Um, so I'm starting to fill out
kind of the very easy sections of that.
So right now I have obviously the name,
the location, the classification under
criteria C. Um the historic and current
functions functions of the building, the
architectural classification, the
materials of the building, the criteria,
the area of significance, the architect
geographical data is all in. Um, so now
it's the big part of doing the
architectural description and the um
narrative, the historical narrative as
well. Um, right when I sent this out,
Casey Worster, I think is how you
pronounce it from Shipo, um, popped into
my office and she's like, "Is that due
in June?" And I was like, "I no,
[laughter] that's due in September." Um,
but she is going to help me. um I
reached out to the contact on the base
but didn't get some great feedback or
resources and so she actually has a
relationship with that person. So she's
going to reach out to them um and
hopefully they can find some
information. Uh the reason for that
being is um the airport terminal the
premise of it even being constructed is
because of the work being done at FE
Warren um during the Cold War. And so
the intention was that that airport was
needed because there would be this
influx of traffic and Cheyenne was going
to be booming and busting in aviation
again. Um so she's going to help me
hopefully track down some of that from
the base perspective.
Um and then I'm going to hopefully get
into the city records and try to find
some minutes. I have some dates around
when it was kind of first talked about
in the city. I don't remember those off
the top of my head, but start going
through city council minutes as well um
to try to pull some more of that
information. So,
great. Does anyone have any questions
for Elizabeth on that? Nope. We'll move
on to oral histories project.
>> Um I don't have any updates this month.
I've been too busy to to work on
anything and it doesn't look like
Patrick did either. So, so no no updates
this time.
>> No worries. All right, we'll move on to
Historic Preservation Month. Um, I guess
recap, we did give the L. Cler Jones
award on Saturday. I thought that that
went pretty well. And thank you, Erin,
for giving the plaque, I'll make sure I
Yeah. Okay, we have it now. I'll make
sure I get that over to them. Um, I
guess if anyone else has any comments to
make on on that event.
saw we were on TV for on uh it's not
channel five, it's the other.
>> Oh,
>> we were on 16 and 27. What was one's
Fox? For some reason, they have the same
news on both channels.
>> Well, cool. Yeah, I know. I thought that
that went well and got a lot of
attention. So, um
>> they were really excited. Everybody
Yeah.
>> Yeah, they were really happy to receive
that award. Um, and then it looks like
the Dubo Award was reopened um
until July 31st. Hopefully we actually
get some. Do Do you know if we've gotten
any applications?
I haven't heard from Matt if we have. I
can check with him though. Okay. So,
hopefully we get some. Oh, go ahead. Um,
and I did post something on our socials
for that and I have it on my calendar to
pay for an ad in mid July um to get that
pumped out too.
>> Oh, awesome. No, that that'd be great.
>> And I would just say that I think um we
we should sort of be thinking ahead in
in case that we don't get any
nominations again that maybe so so that
we're not sort of just like still
waiting and sitting around. So, I think
maybe if it might just be good for us as
a board to all be thinking about um
residences that may be um
you know considered eligible for the
award um as we're waiting for that sort
of July 31st deadline. I agree and I
would offer that maybe we potentially uh
look at if no one else applies the
Sturgeis house. The new um owner of that
has been working to get the exterior uh
fixed up, but she's done a lot on the
interior. It's now kind of a renovable
craft
place. I'm forgetting the name of it,
which is terrible. She she did actually
come to our board
four or five months ago. It's when we
had that weird meeting over at the
police station and she came um to kind
of get some advice and so I I think that
preservation is really important and
I've seen the pictures online of what
she's done. Um but
>> just the weird meeting that happened.
[laughter]
>> Yeah, that was interesting.
Um, but anyways, we we might keep that
one in the back of our mind of of what
she's done and and what I think she's
going to continue to do. So, um, I guess
any other comments?
Okay. Uh, education of the public.
[clears throat]
>> Got a hold of Bill Lindstöm and he does
not have the digital copy of that that
tape that we transferred over. He said
he'd left it on there for two years and
then uh just that's his normal time
period. So he thought somebody would
have downloaded it by then. And uh what
did you say Glenn's last the architect
you thought might have been the one?
>> Oh, Glen Garrett.
>> Garrett. Okay.
Yeah. That I and I
did find the uh name of the gal that had
the VHS tape. I haven't tracked her down
here, but I didn't realize it been three
years since I talked to her. She had a
landline back then. So I'm not sure what
whether my contact information is still
good for her. So,
that's the update I have.
>> Sounds good. Ornaments.
Oh. Oh, I'm so sorry, Ellis. Sorry.
>> That's okay. Um, some social media
stuff. I just wanted to um update on um
some insights that I pulled. So, within
the last two months, as we've been kind
of focusing on this, um we've been up
151% in our views, which is fantastic.
Um, we've gotten quite a new a bunch of
new followers, too, which is exciting to
see. Um, and more people are engaging
with our content, too. So, it's up
that's up
169%. So, I don't know if this is kind
of just a big boom, and I expect it will
level out, but it's exciting to see. Um,
regardless,
um, some proposals that I have for the
next month are on the 15th talking about
the Crow Creek flood of 1883. Um, there
aren't really any photos of that, but I
figured it could be a cool way to show
other floods in town, especially since
there's great um, historic buildings in
the background of that, too. I know some
of these aren't exactly historic
preservation based, but if we wanted to
lean into just some historic photos
showing, you know, the downtown area.
Um, sorry. Go ahead.
>> Didn't mean to cut you up. Um, I don't
know if you already have the photo, but
I have a a photo of that flood that's
outside of um the uh Idleman block
building.
>> Awesome.
>> So, I can send that to you.
>> Perfect.
Um the 22nd is auto race day.
Um there's some great photos showing
different, you know, automobile races
downtown at Frontier Park. Um just again
another one to share some historic
photos around Cheyenne.
Um and then the next day is uh in 1919
of June 23rd is when St. John's Hospital
became the memorial hospital. Um, and
there's some photos of that original
hospital in state archives as well. So,
those are kind of my proposals for
history based ones. Um, and I didn't
know if there was any board info that we
wanted to share this month month as
well.
>> Uh, the core of engineers did history of
of the dry creek and crow flooding back
in the like 1960s.
I know there was copies of those in the
city engineers office when I left a
century ago, but I might even have a
copy of those myself. But uh cuz there
was a the rumor is that that Crow Creek
flood. The flood or the uh Crow Creek
actually was like a block or two over on
like Snider and some buildings went down
and got stuck in the underpass and they
just pushed dirt in and then moved and
built a new crossing at Ames.
So,
>> I do have one social media question
because I I see that people are kind of
sending um private messages and I don't
know if you've been responding to them
or if we should talk about responding to
them, but because some were like, "How
do we research our house?" And I don't
know. Have you have you respond to to
any of those?
>> Um no, I haven't, but thank you for the
reminder. Um I can start doing that. I
mean, I usually check the museum's
messages almost three times a week. So,
there's no reason why I can't switch
profiles and check check ours too. So,
yeah, I can add that to my remember
to-do list.
>> Don't want to add the extra burden, but
I' I've just Yeah, I've seen them and
I'm like, oh,
>> well, kind of. Yeah, I agree. And if
people are engaging, definitely want to
engage back. So, thank you.
>> And Elizabeth, you're asking about like
things from the historic preservation
board that you should share. I just I
don't know if we have any material or if
we got any pictures from Saturday the L
clerk Jones um which I don't know I
don't know what's what we have or where
it where it's at but it would probably
be a good idea to share that we awarded
the L clerk Jones award to the Asher
building. the ones I took are terrible,
but I do know that there that I think
it's your Wyoming link or whatever it
is, they had like the video and I don't
know if maybe we could share that.
>> Um did did you I was just going to
comment that Amber um put together some
really nice like a couple posters that
are on display there. Oh yeah.
>> That have like a timeline of the
building and some interesting facts and
old news articles and stuff. So just
even like a PDF of those images would be
cool to share.
>> Yep. I'll send that to you
>> chair. If I may add real quick because I
because Elizabeth or board member Dryrer
really mentioned some good history um
that had gone on in the community and
something I've tried to plant a seed in
our community recreation uh dire
community recreation events director's
ear is that the pickle ball courts at
Lions Park are actually at the former
location of the Cheyenne Zoo. And if you
ever Google search Cheyenne Zoo to see
what it was like, you get redirected to
Colorado Springs, which I find
disappointing because of the Cheyenne
Mountain Zoo. Although cool, it's not
Cheyenne.
I've I've talked to Jason. I've asked
that we name that the Zoo at Lions Park
because I think it'd be just kind of
cool. A whole bunch of crazy because you
got some wild pickle ball games. But I
think it would be really cool if we were
able to as a board put together some
type of exhibit that would recognize
that this was a zoo because that was
something that was common in some of
these small western towns to to
basically fence in the lost elk bison or
deer that happen to be out there. But I
mean that's what the zoo was. But just
just planting a seed because that seed
hasn't germinated with our CRV group.
But anyway, I like it.
I can I can digress again, but my
grandfather one late night him and his
buddies after a night of drinking went
out there and tried to ride the buffalo.
>> That's an oral history.
>> And three of them ended up um in the
hospitals.
>> That's a great that's a great story. I
like that. So, um I guess anything else
for Elizabeth or Elizabeth, do you have
any other things to share in marketing?
Okay. Um, ornaments.
>> Well, you always hear about authors
having writer's block as a part-time
artist for the ornaments. I've hit some
creativity blocks, but I did submit my
final um today. So, by the next week, I
will have a
copy of what we're going to do. I've
already pre-sold 337 of them. But like I
told you, this is going to be the water
tower, and that's not going to appeal to
the tourists that come through here is
to get a picture of our water tower. So,
I did order reordered uh Capitol Dome
and a few couple hundred and the um
depot to let those folks sell them so we
can continue on with that. Um,
what I need from you guys down front row
is I'm going to put a piece of the paint
they use on those on each ornament on
the back just so there's some
connectivity there. So, if you know
anybody that's up there painting or can
give me access to it. I went up there
and tried to talk to them, but it it's
actually posted it. It looks like, you
know, like I'm going to go to jail if I
cross that fence and go talk to
somebody. So, if anybody knows the
artist, alls I need is about a half
ounce.
>> Yeah, it's it's Jordan and then CHP
paint. I do have Eric McDonald's um
information. Um like are you looking for
the old paint on the paint?
>> Whatever he's using pictures. I just
need the empty can and I can dab it with
that.
>> Okay. Yeah, I I I can send you Eric's
information.
>> That'd be good. Yeah, they've got that
fenced off and signs that say you get
shot on site and
Okay. Um, that's all I had.
>> Okay. Uh, airport fountain planning.
Kelly, do you want to give the update on
that?
>> Yes, ma'am. I'd love to. Um, okay. So,
since our last meeting um last month
when we met um Pacific Coast
Conservation was on site that week doing
all of their testing and reporting. So,
I just received um last week the report
from them and had a chance to read
through that. It's pretty detailed and
explains like the five different fill
materials that she tested in different
areas and then um the paint material
that kind of colors the infills to look
similar to the original terracotta glaze
and a couple of different glaze
materials on top of that. And she's got
a combination of all of these different
products that she's tested and
documented in different areas to see
[sighs]
how those hold up over the next year.
Um, and um, Erin, I just forwarded you
today the invoice along with that that
matches the purchase order amount that
they quoted for us. And I did just want
to note um, looking at that, she
actually exceeded her hours. She
originally quoted like 24 hours for her
to be on site and she worked over 35
hours and then put a little bit of
additional time into the report, but
they did discount that. they treated it
as a not to exceed proposal from what
they had quoted us that at just over
$9,000. So, there was over a $2,000
discount on that um based on the time
that and materials that she's actually
put into it. So, I just wanted to note
that. I think that's good of them. They
didn't come back and ask for additional
fees or anything like that. She truly
did as much as she could while she was
here that week.
Um, and then second, we um the
subcommittee went out and met with Jason
Sanchez last week as well to get a
better idea of what he's seen. Um, last
year specifically, he said the city had
to put some money into replacing the
pump. Um, come to find out, cuz there
was a little bit of confusion like, oh,
we think it's new. We know it was
operational. Nobody was really sure. He
said they actually um fried like the
motherboard or some part on that pump
last year, so he had to replace it. So
that's brand new. Most of the plumbing
and everything in the vault below the
fountain is new. He confirmed except for
there's a main like supply pipe that
goes
from the vault underground and comes up
and feeds the main
reservoir.
Yeah. So like the inner part of the
fountain. Yeah. That's got a circular
pipe running all around and it's got
like the supply nipples I guess that the
fountain sprays out of. Um, so that
circular part and then the the supply
pipe that goes down to the vault below
are old and corroded. And that was
Jason's um main point and request to us
is he said, you know, they did a bunch
of investigation and had guys out there
every time the fountain was clogged and
not working, they'd have to go out and
clean it out and they replaced multiple
things. was working with a plumber last
summer. He said, but he is pretty sure
like through all of the time that they
spent out there that this is the last
piece of that puzzle, like as far as the
plumbing and the components that make
the fountain run, that definitely need
to be replaced. He told us like there's
no point in the city even trying to fill
the fountain and start it up this year
until that can be replaced. And so what
he requested of us is that if we are um
willing and the board thinks it's
appropriate for us to designate some
additional funds from the the will
bequest um money to allow him to go out
to a contractor and get a quote for
replacement of those components because
basically he said it's old and corroded
and the metal and rust and everything
inside of those pipes flakes off and and
clogs their filters almost immediately
and it's just a maintenance nightmare
for them to try to get guys out there to
clear it out and keep it running. Um, so
he did not have any quotes on that yet.
Didn't know specifically what it's going
to cost, but he asked if we would
approve up to like 20 or $25,000.
He's fairly confident and I would I
don't know either, but I can't imagine
it would cost that much. I would assume
it should come under under that. and if
he can get a quote. I can't remember
what the maximum number is, but he
doesn't have to go out for competitive
bids. He said he'd just like to take
care of it.
>> Yeah, if it's it's a if it's under
10,000, [clears throat] but yeah, but if
it is over that, then he does have to
get three competitive bids to do that.
But I think the reason why he's asking,
sorry Kelly, that um
for that 20 to 25,000 is kind of the
other miscellaneous pieces to the
fountain that they can work on repairing
like the glass above. Look at some of
the sealants which we'd want to talk to.
And he's he's mentioned a couple of
companies that we can talk to as far as
um fountain repair and just making sure
that we have a good seal um that upper
basin. um it could have some kind of
leaks in it. We want to make sure that
weather barrier is completely intact.
And so part of that 20 to 25,000 is to
try and take care of those items. We're
going to have to break that seal anyways
when we put in new piping. So we're
going to have to repair at least around
there. So we hopefully have someone kind
of take a look at that. So sorry, go
ahead.
>> Yeah. No, thank you. So there's there's
a few additional components that we'd
like to um try to get additional experts
involved. I guess he mentioned I think
is it Sawyer
um
Sawyer Landscaping or something that has
may have some fountain related or water
feature related experience we could
reach out to. and then global spa. And
then Jason said he could send us the
name of the designer that was working on
potential updates for Johnson pool as
well. So that's um one of our next steps
as well is to reach out to a couple of
those contacts and see if we can get
somebody to look at the fountain from
like a waterproofing perspective and try
to identify what the potential issues
are there. Those were other components
that were also included in the report
from Pacific Coast Conservation is that
they would not recommend, you know, them
coming out and doing any additional
repairs to the terracotta itself until
we make sure the fountain is waterproof
and all of the plumbing is in good
working order and there's not like water
infiltration. One of the other things
that I think Amber alluded to is like
around the outside base wall where the
fountain terracotta blocks meet the
concrete, there's a pretty wide um grout
joint that is like broken out pretty
much all the way around. And that was
one of the comments we got originally is
that if water isn't draining properly
away from the fountain, there could be
rain water and ground water and you know
fountain water from the wind or whatever
seeping in that way as well. So, she did
Lucinda while she was here did repair
like one section of that grout, but we
talked about that could be something
that potentially we could incorporate
with this
$25,000
um depending on where quotes come in to
have a mason repair the rest of the way
around that because they're probably
going to have to like grind out, clean
up, and then re mortar that joint.
and and Jason asked for it to happen
this way is so that every time he gets a
quote, he's not having to come to this
board for approval and then we drag this
out for a very long time. If we could
give him this this funding, he could
potentially get the fountain running
maybe the last week in the fall, which
we need in order to understand how what
Pacific Coast has done, how that water
is acting.
>> [clears throat]
>> um if we can't get the fountain running
at all, then it kind of hurts this kind
of investigation that we've already paid
for. Um so that's that's kind of why
we're asking for it in this this way
instead of saying, "Hey, Jason, go get
all these quotes and then come back
because we might drag this out for
another 68 months just in that process."
So I guess any Sorry. Did you have
anything else to add? Is there any
questions?
So, first of all, thank you guys for
doing all I know how much work it is
sort of trying to like piece all these
different things together and so I'm
just trying to make sure I sort of fully
understand like so the recommendation
from so Pacific Coast came and like
investigated and they're um
looking at the different like finishes
or different repair methods but for
whatever testing they're doing they have
they have to wait a full year before
they can come back and actually do the
terracotta
anyways.
And so you're saying that in the
meantime we can
try to finish these last few items that
need to be addressed before and they
need to be addressed before the
terracotta is repaired anyway.
>> Okay. So
>> yeah,
>> that's correct. and and because a part
of this your test is she wants the
fountain to run and at this point
Jason's like we're we're not we're not
feeling this and turning it on because
it's not it's not functioning properly.
So,
>> okay. So, to complete the test
>> Mhm.
>> and we need to turn the we need to be
able to turn the fountain on a year from
now and or whenever they come back. and
Jason it was like there's no point in
even doing that unless we are
>> fixing these other things like we need
to fix the plumbing this summer
>> because it has to be
>> yes
>> water
>> or underwater water through the system
in order to guarantee that that one of
whatever well one of the different
methods or possibly more than one method
of terra cotta repair works.
>> Yep, that's correct. And at the very
latest, we'd have to have water running
by next spring um for this
[clears throat] to work out. But
ideally, if we can do this and get all
the plumbing repairs and waterproofing
done by like September and at least run
the fountain for a week, that would that
would be fantastic.
Um,
I understand I understand that
the next fix is the plumbing fix, which
is what Jason is talking about. The one
thing that concerns me is that um I
would hope the city has some skin in
this game as well as the board. Um, and
it it just concerns me a little bit that
Jason's asking us to fund the whole
25,000
I would much prefer
joining in a partnership with a city.
They pay half and we pay half. I mean,
it's it I you know, I'm we're not made
of money. I know we have a an endowment,
but I'm I'm you know, uh this is a this
is a wonderful uh fountain that's that's
that's part of this city. And um you
know I'm I'm just a little bit
dumbfounded that they're asking us to
put up all the money and um that's just
I
>> I that's my that's my knee-jerk
reaction. I
>> I definitely don't disagree with you. I
I mean I I agree but unfortunately
because they never allocated any funds
for this budget, you know, for what they
do to the fountain. You correct me if
I'm wrong, Charles, but this is just
what Jason indicated to me is that they
they don't have any funds to put toward
the fountain.
>> Yep.
>> They are providing kind of work in kind,
you know, the the employees are
>> the laborending
it's city funds are paying for the
people that are cleaning the filters and
all that stuff. So,
>> Charles,
>> chair, members of the board, there
wasn't any funding that was allocated
with the budget. Um, there are a couple
of options that we do have to seek
funding. One of them would be looking at
some of our our uh there's a lot of
philanthropic money out there lately
because of recent development like
Metahazer Community Action grants,
Microsoft has grants, a lot of the other
data center developers are trying to
outdo themselves with monies that they
donate. Um, so there could be the option
to uh look at that including tall grass
as well.
>> That's great because I agree Patrick. It
it feels like there should be some sort
of partnership in in getting this taken
care of. So if there is avenues um
>> we also do do budget reappropriations
um quarterly is what the city treasurer
would do. So, if we would like to look
at a specific line item for a 50/50
match, that is something that we could
see if council member Escoel would like
to bring forward and it could be a
discussion point. We could look at
pulling that from our reserves. So I do
have one question though is I mean I I
do agree that it would be great to have
the this process of getting additional
money but
>> will that delay and that's kind of the
problem if if we can move forward with
this of what our funds is is there a way
that we can kind of sort of get a
reimbursement for what we've done or
maybe we look at our next step as being
a 5050 match.
Chair, I I don't think reimbursement
would be a realistic expectation just
with what I've seen from how the
government here works. Uh but next steps
definitely something that would
would be reasonable.
>> Gary,
>> so let me take you back 10 or 11 years
ago. We decided to fix the fountain as a
board. We said we would take care of it.
We started with ornaments. The endowment
we got was directly to be paid to take
care of that fountain. If we get now we
start going after the city to pay
something, you're only going to delay a
process that we've drugg on
for a a career. Um the fact is we said
we would take care of that. We've got
the money to do it. We've dedicated all
the money from several of those projects
to take care of this. Um, I I've said
this before. It's time to get moving and
get things over with instead of turning
this into a lifelong project.
>> We've got the funds. Let's get going and
get
>> Would you like to make that a motion?
>> I don't I don't like the idea of giving
somebody a blank check either. Um, but
>> no.
>> Um,
>> and that's why I think we would we would
c
>> start asking the city for money. I I'll
guarantee I I won't be here on this
board when that happens and probably
half of you won't be if we drag this on
any longer.
I have just sorry I have just one more
question. Um
I'm trying to remember back from one or
two months ago about what the um I'm
just thinking about, you know, the the
will cost we have is a certain amount of
money. We spent some of it for um this
initial testing from Pacific Coast.
Seems like we're getting ready to to
maybe vote on um spending some more of
it on the the plumbing and getting that
all taken care of. Will we have enough
of that left over to finish the
terracotta with Pacific Coast afterwards
based on their initial estimate?
>> That's a great question. I'm trying to
think of what that number was.
>> Yeah, I looked it up. Um, so when we had
our strategic planning meeting a couple
months ago, that fund was right at about
155,000
and so we've spent just over nine. So
we've got roughly 145 left. If we
approve the up25 for these repairs, we'd
be at around 120 if we spent all of
that. So looking at that, I mean, I
don't know what the remaining repairs
through Pacific Coast will cost.
Um, but to me, I felt a little bit
optimistic, I guess, looking at that,
realizing like we still will have over
$100,000 fund that's been given
specifically for the fountain. um if we
can figure out some sort of like
remaining repairs and get a quote from
Pacific Coast a year from now and have a
a better idea of what that's going to
take and then there will be some ongoing
like spot treatment and infills and
things like that if we can work out some
sort of agreement
with the city between this fund and
their funds potentially um to set aside
some money for Pacific Coast to come
back and keep it in good condition. Um,
I feel like there still could be some
funds left over to do some interpretive
signage or some small amount of
beautifification. It may not be the
full, you know, think design we were
thinking originally, but
I think the
the main
purpose of that endowment was
specifically for the fountain. And I've
heard that it's important to several
board members and I think to the
community to keep it functioning and
running as an actual fountain. So I
think these are the things that have to
be done first to do that.
>> Carrie,
were you wanting to
No, you're just
>> if we spend every penny we've got, that
would be the time to go to the city and
say, "Look, we just spent $147,000
on this. we need x amount to finish
this. We're in a much better position.
And by the way, when we started these
ornaments, I said I would only do that
if we dedicated all that money going
strictly to the fountain. After we got
the fountain fixed and thought it was
done, we um
put it in the open fund. I would propose
to you that we need to go back to
dedicating the ornament funds to go to
the found and out of general. But we've
got back to my original point. We've got
a much better leverage of getting money
out of the city if we say look we just
spent this much money and we need this
much to finish it and there's not a
person sitting up here that that's on
that council would say we're not going
to do that. I don't think maybe Charles,
just go with it. [laughter]
>> Okay. I guess any any other questions?
Would anyone like to make a motion to
dedicate the 25,000 to the plumbing
repair and waterproofing repair and
what we need to get this to run?
>> I will make such a motion and I'd second
it. Any further discussion?
>> Um, can I off can I offer a friendly
amendment that um the city provide a
detailed analysis uh explanation of all
the funds that were expended and what
they were expended for?
>> Absolutely. Yes.
David, will you okay or I'm okay with
that amendment?
>> Okay.
All in favor say I. I.
>> Any opposed?
All right. Motion passes.
>> Now, I'd like to make a motion that all
the funds and profits we receive from
the ornaments from this day forward go
back into the fountain fund.
>> I second the motion.
>> Any discussion?
No. All in favor say I. I. I.
I.................... Any opposed.
Motion passes.
Okay. Um, we'll move on to the pump
house. I think we all know that it was
unfortunately set on fire and it looks
like uh there's potential that the
investigation still ongoing as far as
the structural. Do you have any updates
on that?
>> Chair, members of the board, I did reach
out to the chief of staff to figure out
where it was in the process. They have
presently had a structural analysis
that's occurred. They've been working on
it. They're finalizing that report and
they do anticipate to have that ready in
the next probably within the next week
or so. So, as soon as we have that
information, we will get that over to
you. From what I understand
preliminarily is I I think it's not as
bad as people may have thought when it
was having its issues. It It may have
made it easier to repurpose. So I don't
I I
>> it's nice way of putting it. This will
be careful of what the public perceives
on.
>> So but anyway there's you know it
changes the way that the repurposing
would look because before it was
historic structure you had to match you
had to retrofit stuff like that. Um and
they're evaluating if there's anything
that's salvageable still within the roof
or if the roof can be completely
rebuilt. Um I'm just happy that with
that structure that the walls are still
there. are still intact. Um I watched
this occur on that that evening and uh
was just surprised that it didn't just
fall. Um, back when I was in Little
Rock, Arkansas in 2004
in 2005, we actually had a a Masonic
temple that was um undergoing a
rehabilitation
um of a CLG grant, the CLG grant for it,
and it had been through its own delays
and hoops. There was embezzlement of a
first CLG fund and there's a second CLG
award that had had moved forward on it.
And right when it was almost o ready for
open, a homeless person had lit a fire
inside and it burned and the entire core
of the building burned out and the
facade just fell um into the street and
there's bricks everywhere. and that
building was restored and that building
is standing as now a black history
museum in Little Rock um Arkansas and
downtown um because it was um part of
what was their I believe is our
African-American heritage district or I
don't know if you know anything about
that board member Deg Grryer is it grer
right deg grer degraier
>> it's degraier
>> degraier just last name
>> sorry yes but anyway um it's the focal
point of the African-American heritage
in Little Rock So, it's a success story.
>> Gary
>> Charles, are there any plans to tear
down that debris? I mean, it seems like
that's a real liability to have a bunch
of burnt roofing stuff hanging out.
Chair, members of the board, uh through
you to uh board member Sims. Um there
will be plans to demolish what can be
demolished, what needs to be demolished
or removed. I know they're still going
through that investigation and still
going through that survey, but as soon
as it's safe to do so and we can get a
contractor on board, they'll do that.
>> Fantastic. Does anyone else have
>> question? Charles, was there any
insurance on the building at all?
>> No, it was uninsurable.
>> Yeah,
>> it's just hail damage, right?
>> Yeah, it has no utilities, no fireproof.
Yeah, I don't think anyone would ensure
that right now. Chair, members of the
board, one thing I would note is that
the Metropolitan Planning Organization
had been looking at doing a pedestrian
uh and access plan for the Ames
underpass and how that greenway tied in
with the uh pump house structure when it
was proposed for uh reuse for non- city
purposes. I believe in the upcoming uh
agenda for our metropolitan planning
organization, they may look at scaling
back uh some of of that project because
with it being more of a municipal use,
uh they're looking at how can they
evaluate the entire transportation
system there uh to make it work better
for everybody and provide a better uh
pedestrian crossing of that greenway
trail. Long story short, they're looking
at limiting Day Avenue and potentially
adding a hawk signal, one of those
flashing pedestrian crossings, so to
provide safe crossing from the greenway
along day to the greenway on the eastern
side of Ames.
Cool.
Guess any other comments on pump house
before you move on?
>> Okay. Um the design guidelines, uh we've
we've been kind of working through
those. We do have a little bit of an
outline. Um, one thing that I I think
someone was going to send me, I can't
remember who, but there was a 1990s
version of the design guidelines, and I
I I had access to it at some point, and
now I don't. Do Do you guys know where
those 1990s design guidelines
live where I could find them?
>> Was it See, I couldn't Okay.
Okay. Well, we yeah, our subcommittee
will meet meet soon on that. Um, we
would ideally like to have some sort of
kind of outline draft by August in order
to take to the DDA and kind of show them
our progress. So, that's where we are at
this point. Any questions on design
guidelines?
No. Okay. The watch list items, I don't
know if we really need to go through
each one of those. Um, unless anyone
wants to discuss any of the watch list
items in particular. No. Um, all right.
New business, the Bridger Tower
Corporation, Telecommunications Tower.
Um, I don't know. Have you guys had a
chance to run through this and and what
they are proposing?
No. Um, do do you want to give an
explanation or
or I can I can tell you my
interpretation. Okay. So, I I did
receive this in the mail. It is a
section 106 process. Um, what they're
looking at putting up is a
telecommunications tower, which is if
you go down Horse Creek and it splits
off and this kind of wanders down the
ways a little bit, there's that white
analopee barn that's like a a new
wedding venue.
Anyways, they're they're just looking to
put a tower up on this property and um
there is a do you have like a satellite
image version of this space there in my
from what I see I don't see anything s
historically significant around it. Um I
didn't see that it impeded on anything
but I don't know if anyone else had a
chance to to take a look at this. Josh,
>> my only comment and I can't remember how
all it says it is. Uh,
>> do does it say on there?
>> Uh,
>> I think it did. I can't read that far
away
>> because I think it says, but
the the only thing Oh, 199 ft
approximate overall of 199 ft. Yeah. Um,
my my only question is that they would
maybe want to talk with the the base,
which I'm sure they are that because the
base is a national historic landmark,
right? Um, and so I don't know if it
would be within the the site disrupt the
viewshed of the national historic
landmark of FE Warren or not. Um, and I
don't know if that's something that we
would get involved with since it's sort
of outside of this is outside of city
limits, right? Like way far out there.
Um, so I don't know that it's really
something we would get involved with,
but I don't know. That was my only
thought was that the base might the
basis cultural resources person might
think about the viewshed, but I have no
idea if they would be able to see it
from there.
>> That's a great question. This is outside
of the city. So do we even have
>> chair members of the board as being the
CLG the certified local government you
are the ones who okay basically have the
opinion or take do the statements for
anything in Larmy County.
>> So if the base were to apply for
historic preservation grant uh through
shipo would come through this this
board. Um if there was a preservation
grant through for like certified local
government grant CLG grant for like
Burns or Alban they'd come through this
board as well. Okay. Oh, good to know.
So, I guess
I at least for me, this is the first
section 106 that has come to the board
while I've been on. So, I guess I'm not
sure what we need to
approve or deny or I I guess what's our
process here,
>> chair, members of the board, with the
section 106
um process, what's going on is they are
proposing a tower. They're using they're
going through the NEPA process and as
part of the NEPA process they're
required to reach out to a whole bunch
of different entities including the
state historic preservation office and
and the CLG um for the county. So that's
what triggers this. We've had two of
these that I've been involved in in
southeast Wyoming. One of them was the
old uh WCO railroad in Laramie that used
to connect Laramie to the WCO area. That
was a rail line that went out to
Centennial. When they pulled up the
tracks out there, that was a culturally
significant line. So they looked at,
well, how can we remediate the removal
of of that and then that time they saved
some of the pertinances for the railroad
and they put them in the railroad park.
Um, so that was there. Here we had the
Persian uh street bridge over the Union
Pacific Rail Line. It was one of the
last remaining bridges over the
transcontinental railroad um to exist
and may have been the last one and it
barely existed. It had become
structurally deficient
>> um for the Lincoln Highway. That's
Lincoln Highway crossing and the
mitigation there um that was proposed
and accepted was uh basically a a plaque
that recogniz the Lincoln Highway was
restoration of a plaque over on Kerry
and Lincoln Way. Um so in this case
and with any cell phone tower we often
get these as well because they're going
through the FCC, the Federal
Communications Commission. So they'll
ask is there any type of historical
significance out here? Um, so they're
really just looking for any any
statements as to whether or not you all
are aware of anything. I'm not aware of
anything out that direction.
>> I'm I'm not aware of anything, but is
this something that we have to make any
um forward movement in in this meeting
or is it something that we could move
bring to our next meeting? cuz I I mean
I certainly don't have enough education
of this specific site and or
understanding this process for me to
feel comfortable making any sort of
motion. I mean I don't I don't know how
others feel.
>> Chair members of the board um we'd have
until July
4th but it'll carry on the next business
day which will be I believe July 6th to
make comment on this. So it would have
to be something at this meeting.
>> Oh.
>> Um
>> you don't have to make a comment. Um
absence of a comment is no comment.
>> Okay.
>> So if you formally wanted to make a
comment, we just do that. You all are
welcome to authorize the chair just to
make a comment if anything is found by a
board member.
>> Okay. So I guess from now until July
before July 4th, if anyone has anything
particular on the site that they want
issue a comment, send it to me and then
we can send it to
to make a motion to authorize her to do
that on our behalf.
>> Yeah, go ahead. Sure.
>> That would be great if you all had a
motion to authorize that to occur.
>> I I would make the motion to authorize
Amber to uh make a comment on behalf of
the board by the deadline. Um if uh
something comes to light, I'll second.
>> Any further discussion? No. Um yeah, I
actually had a question. Um, if the
first thing that comes to mind is if
there's a historic ranch nearby. Um, and
then if there is, but we give the
go-ahad to construct, are they providing
mitigation funds?
>> That's what the process is.
>> That's what we're figuring out right
now. As chair, members of the board,
what it is, if we note that there is
something of potential significance like
the viewshed from a historic ranch uh
that's nearby, then that would be found
in their in their application and then
it would start that conversation as what
is appropriate mitigation.
>> And we're just for clarification also,
we're not giving what anything we do is
not giving approval for construction. We
could just have the opportunity to
comment on it. So whether we say
something or not, it has no bearing on
whether anything for
>> and I'm sorry if I missed this, but
Shipo has the ultimate authority.
Is that correct?
Who's doing the actual approving?
>> Chair, members of the board, I believe
it's Chipo, but I think we ultimately
have the ultimate authority. I have to
double check.
>> We meaning us or we meaning you.
[laughter] that I've noticed what has
happened in in these cases. I understand
that the shipo will defer that to us and
then we have to execute any necessary
agreements
that are needed to ensure that that
preservation element exists. For
example, the
uh Louisa Swain federal building which
we're still going through. I I believe
we finally figured out what's going on.
There is
the previous chair Miller Simpson had
negotiated some discussions directly
with uh the government services
administration GSA on that disposal and
it should have gone through an agreement
with the Shipo office first and it
skipped that process but the GSA doesn't
realize that. So there's a bunch of
pieces it's messy. There's a bunch of
pieces that need to fall in line and
those pieces are out of order right now
for the Louis Swain. It's not threatened
right now. It's just delayed which
federal government they create delays.
Why not participate in one?
Okay. So, I guess the point is is we we
we don't get to have the say.
Unfortunately, we don't have
clarification of who makes the final
decision, but the motion is to allow any
comments that you guys have to filter to
me then for me to pass on to um this
project. So, is there any other
questions or further discussion? Okay.
And all in favor say I.
>> I. I. I.
>> Any opposed?
>> Motion passes.
>> Okay. I just a followup question for
Charles. Do you know if the mitigation
was completed for that uh that other one
we were talking about? I haven't look
gone and looked at the sign that they
were supposed to fix. And chair, members
of the board, I believe it has been
completed. If I do recall, I asked uh
Stephanie Low who was working with the
DOT at that time um if it had been done
and she had indicated has been done and
I believe I saw it once but I can't
really recall. It didn't didn't stand
out enough to be like yep I did do think
I verified once but right down the
street
on Pioneer Lincoln way.
>> Yep. Sorry to go backwards one more time
and maybe I'm jumping the gun on this.
Um, if there is mitigation, who is that
going to and is there an application
process to receive it?
And members of the board, uh,
the question was who's authorized to
receive the mitigation? Um, typically
that would go through the board to the
governing body. If mitigation is is
needed, it would go through this board
recommendation and then a formal
agreement to the governing body.
Um, old business, David Palasio,
he didn't show up online. Okay. Well,
guess we'll move on. Other business time
sheets
Aaron
>> chair. So I sent an email with a copy of
time sheets and then we also have copies
out in the um foyer every time we have a
meeting. So if you guys are working out
even when we're at these meetings, you
can put that down as time on your on
your time sheets. Um anytime you guys
are meeting elsewhere, you can put that
time down, but we really want to get
those in. Um, and especially for
um, the CLG grants that we have out
there. Um, we we use those as in kind
match for some of those.
I know I've been terrible about doing
it, but I very much appreciate you
sending it digitally because that'll
make it easier for me. But yeah, if we
could all work on that.
>> Are you supposed to be monthly or yearly
or doesn't really? It'd be great if it
was monthly,
but you know, catch up on the last six
months. You know that also works.
[laughter]
>> Okay. Do you want those sent to you,
Erin?
You can send them to me.
Oh. Um, how far back do you want it to
go? Cuz I don't even remember the last
time I turned what?
>> Um, at least this year would be good.
Since January. Yeah, I I think when we
submitted our report, our yearly report,
we had already kind of discussed
previous year. So, anything last year
probably is mute at this point, but I
think the year starts in like October or
something.
>> That's what I was going to say. October.
The year starts October one. So, you can
go back through anything through October
we could use in next year's report,
>> I think. Yeah.
>> Thank you. That's a good point. Okay.
Okay. Well, if there's no other
business, I guess we will adjourn.
Okay. All right. Yay. Can we do it?
Okay.
It didn't work.